<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the Right Honourable, the knights, citizens, and burgesses, the Parliament of England, assembled at Westminster, the humble appeale and petition of Mary Overton, prisoner in Bridewell:.</title>
            <author>Overton, Mary.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90224</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O617</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E381_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201411</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861925</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861925</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114071</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90224)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114071)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 61:E381[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the Right Honourable, the knights, citizens, and burgesses, the Parliament of England, assembled at Westminster, the humble appeale and petition of Mary Overton, prisoner in Bridewell:.</title>
                  <author>Overton, Mary.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Per me Mary Overton.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March 24 1646".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Overton, Mary --  Imprisonment --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Overton, Richard, fl. 1646 --  Imprisonment --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Detention of persons --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Civil rights --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114071:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO The right Honourable, the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes, the Parliament of England, aſſembled at Weſtminſter, <hi>The humble Appeale and Petition of</hi> Mary Overton, <hi>priſoner in Bridewell:</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>SHEWETH,</opener>
            <p>THat whereas the publike ſafety and liberty of the <hi>people</hi> is the maine end of all Government, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, whether Regall, Parliamentarie, or other; and the Law of the Land uſually called the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law,</hi> being grounded upon right reaſon and equity, the true Rule and Directory, both for ruling and obeying, which to preſerve, as the King declareth in his Anſwer to your Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of the 23. of May, 1643. <hi>ought to bee the perpetuall and vigilant care of a Prince,</hi> and acknowledgeth, that <hi>upon the obſervation of the Fundamentall Lawes, the publike hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe and welfare of the people is founded and conſtituted;</hi> calling God to witneſſe, <hi>That the preſervation of the Law, and the Liberty of the People, ſhould alwaies be as much his care and induſtry, as the life or lives of his deareſt children;</hi> profeſſing, <hi>to make the Law the meaſure of his Power, and that there was no man ſo neare unto him in place or affection, whom hee would not leave to the juſtice of the Law;</hi> himſelfe acknowledging <hi>the Law to be the Inheritance of every Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and the only ſecurity hee can have for his life, liberty, or eſtate, the which being neglected, violated, or diſeſteemed under what ſpecious ſhewes or pretences ſoever, a very great meaſure of infelicity, if not irreparable confuſion would in a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>voydably enſue;</hi> and that he was <hi>reſolved not only to obſerve the Lawes himſelfe, but to maintaine them againſt all oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:114071:2"/>
and the Law reſpecteth nothing more then the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Freedome of a mans perſon, according to the ancient and grave Lawyer <hi>Forteſeue, Impius &amp; crudelis eſt, qui li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertati non favet: Angliae Jura in omni caſu libertati dant favorem;</hi> yet notwithſtanding theſe ſo many reiterated profeſſions and aſſeverations, ſo often emitted in the Kings Declarations and Anſwers, and other golden baites of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and preferment, neither your Petitioners husband (now priſoner in Newgate by the Houſe of Lords) nor your Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner could in the leaſt wiſe be induced to comply with the King or his party againſt this honourable Houſe, as many thouſands have done, who now are at liberty, and under your protection, to your high diſhonour, and to the great griefe of your beſt and moſt faithfull friends: but being confident that you the betruſted of the Kingdome, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your many Vowes and Proteſtations, Covenants, Declarations, Remonſtrances, Ordinances, and to the high and great Truſt repoſed in you, would have long ere now improved all your endeavours, powers, and intereſts for the redemption and advancement of our antient (though of late yeares much invaded) Rights, Lawes and Liberties, which are our Birthright and Inheritance, as you (as well as the King) have often told us, <hi>calling God to witneſſe, that the peace and good of the people ever was your only aimes; profeſſing unto us in the preſence of the all-ſeeing Diety, that our peace and ſafety is the onely end of all your Counſells, and endeavours, reſolving therein to continue free from all private aimes, or perſonall reſpects whatſoever: and that you never intended to introduce any new Law to our prejudice, much leſſe to exerciſe any arbitrary power at all, but to your utmoſt to prevent it, holding it your duty to uſe your beſt endeavours that the meaneſt of the Commonalty might enjoy their Rights, Liberty, and Benefits of the Law, being equally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted and entitulled thereto, with the greateſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi> confeſſing and acknowledging, that the ſitting of the PARLIAMENT ought not to <hi>ſuſpend the Law,</hi> the execution thereof according to equity, being
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114071:2"/>
               <hi>the very Spirit</hi> (as you tell us) <hi>which gives life to authority;</hi> from all which and manifold other Premiſes, and Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, even out of your owne mouths, the Commonalty of England are invited and enabled juſtly to challenge and expect from this Houſe the juſt defence, preſervation, and fruition of all their Rights, Lawes, and Liberties, in their lives, perſons and eſtates, reſtraint of, and protection againſt the malice and fury o thoſe that ſeeke their ruine, by any ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary domination, or other practiſes whatſoever; and therefore for that end are all obliged to ſtand by you, and for you: but on the contrary, to return contrary effects, for <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariorum contraria ſunt conſequentia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now ſo it is, though your Petitioners husband hath conſtantly adhered to the Parliament, and hath given ample teſtimony of his ſincere and upright affections to this hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſe, to the juſt Lawes and Freedomes of England in generall, and to the Rights and Properties of all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Commoner in particular, by his conſtant and faithfull endeavours to that end, as many hundreds in the City, yea (I may take the boldneſſe to ſay) many thouſands in the Kingdome can witneſſe in his behalfe, yet notwithſtanding upon the 11. of Auguſt, 1646. had his houſe ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with divers armed men with ſwords and mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, under the Conduct of one <hi>Robert Eales,</hi> and by the ſaid <hi>Robert Eales</hi> (Deputy-Catchpole to the Houſe of Lords) with his Sword drawne in his hand, and by one M. <hi>Eveling</hi> (dweller at the greene Dragon in the Strand) with his piſtoll ready cock'd, was ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly and violently entred, and his perſon laid hold of, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Warrant either Legall or pretended firſt ſhewen, and ſo by force of arms was in an hoſtile manner led captive to the Houſe of Lords, who would (High-Commiſſion-like) have examined him againſt himſelfe; which he refuſing, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing to this honourable Houſe as his proper and compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Judges, was therefore by the Lords, under the pretence of contempt to that Houſe, committed to the infamous Goale of Newgate, there to be kept til their pleaſures ſhould
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114071:3"/>
be further ſignified; Which (as your Petitioner humbly conceiveth) tendeth to the high violation of the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Lawes of this Land, the utter ſubverſion of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Liberties of the people, and of your Petitioners hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands native Right and Inheritance in particular, for by the great Charter of Liberties the Lords cannot paſſe Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon any Commoner in caſes criminall concerning life, liberty, or eſtate, neither can any other Court or Juſtices whatſoever, before Indictment or preſentment, or by other due proceſſe in Law, take away Commoners life, liberty, or goods; nor ought any man by Law, to be forced by Oath to anſwer to Interregatories to accuſe himſelfe in any crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall cauſes, which concerne either his life, liberty, loſſe of goods, or freehold, but ought to bee convicted firſt by witneſſes, preſentment, or the verdict of twelve men, or upon or by his owne voluntarie confeſſion without oath or co-action, as by the Lawes, Statutes, and Authorities here ſet downe, is clearly proved.</p>
            <p>The Statute of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> (31. times confirmed in Parliament) cap. 29. Enacts, <hi>That no Free-man ſhall be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, or impriſoned, or diſſeaſed of his Freehold or Liberties, or free Cuſtomes, or out-lawed, or exiled, or otherwiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed: neither will we paſſe upon him, nor condemne him, but by lawfull Judgement of his Peers, or by the Law of the Land.</hi> Now what is underſtood by the Law of the Land, theſe enſuing Statutes yet in force, declare and explaine. The Statute of 5. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 9. ordains, <hi>That no man from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth ſhall be attached for any Accuſation, nor fore-judged of life, nor limbe, againſt the forme of the great Charter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Statute of the 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4. enacts, <hi>That from henceforth none ſhall be taken by Petition or Suggeſtion made to the King, or to his Councell, unleſſe it be by Indictment and preſentment of good and lawfull men, where ſuch deeds bee done, in due manner, or by proceſſe made by Writ Originall at the Common-Law, &amp;c. and if any thing be done againſt the ſame, it ſhalbe redreſſed, and holden for none.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Statute of 28. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3. provides <hi>That none of what eſtate or condition that he bee, ſhall be taken or impriſoned,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114071:3"/>
without being brought to anſwer by due proceſſe of Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Statute of 42. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3. complaines and concludes thus, <hi>To eſchew the miſchiefs and dammages done to divers of the Commoners by falſe accuſers, which have often times made their accuſations more for vengeance and ſingular profit, then for the profit of the King, or of his People, of which accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed perſons ſome have been impriſoned, and others cauſed to come before the Kings Councell by Writ, and otherwiſe upon grievous paine againſt the Law: It is aſſented and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the good Government of the people, that none be put to anſwer without preſentment before Juſtices, or other matter of Record, or by due Proceſſe, or by ſome Writ Originall, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the old Law of the Land; and if any thing from henceforth be done the contrary, it ſhall be void in Law and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den for errour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe recited Statutes are mentioned and ratified as the undoubted Lawes and Liberties of the Kingdome, by the late Petition of Right, 3. <hi>Caroli.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Statute of 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 14. recites, <hi>That it ſtandeth not with the right order of juſtice nor good equity, that any perſon ſhould be convict and put to the loſſe of his life, name, or goods, unleſſe it be by due accuſation and witneſſe, or by preſentment, verdict, confeſſion, or Proceſſe of Outlawry: ſince by the Law of the Realme no man can be put to death for treaſon committed to the perill of the Kings moſt royall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, but by Preſentment, Verdict, Confeſſion or Proceſſe of Outlawry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Statute of 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> c. 1. enacts, that no man ſhall be indicted or arraigned for any offence againſt the Law, but by two ſufficient Witneſſes at the leaſt, and that <hi>viva voce,</hi> face to face, if they be alive, or within the Realme. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon given in the Law-books againſt inforced Oaths, is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no man is bound to bewray himſelfe in things which concerne his credit, liberty, life, or forfeiture of his eſtate; in which caſes any may lawfully refuſe to take an oath, or give any anſwer at all, as theſe Law-Authorities conclude and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve. 49. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. 2. <hi>a. Fitz. Challenge.</hi> 100. <hi>Brooke</hi> 25. 7. <hi>H.</hi> 4. 10. <hi>a. Fitz.</hi> Juſtice of Peace. 172. <hi>Cromptons</hi> Juſtice
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114071:4"/>
of Peace, 182. 219. 2. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 33. <hi>Dier.</hi> 288. p. 51.</p>
            <p>Alſo many godly Martyrs have by their doctrine and practice taught and affirmed it a thing contrary to the Law of God, of nature, equity, common reaſon, and to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and Civill Law it ſelfe, for men to bewray and accuſe themſelves; and therefore refuſed to take any oaths, or to anſwer any Articles to accuſe themſelves, declaring againſt ſuch oaths and proceedings as Antichriſtian, bloody, tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall, unnaturall, uncharitable, unreaſonable, unjuſt, yea ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecrable and diabolicall. <hi>Fox Acts and Monuments,</hi> printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1510. <hi>pag.</hi> 950, 951. 1006. 1022. 1643. 1616. 1661. 1777. 1778. 1813. 1814. 1815. 1849. 1872. 1873. And the Ancients (called the Fathers) as <hi>Athanaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Ambroſe, Chryſoſtome,</hi> and many others, mentioned by <hi>Sextus Senenſis in Bibliotheca ſancta,</hi> l. 6. p. 434, 435. as well as Moderne Writers, have all paſſed joynt ſentence of condemnation againſt thoſe ſelfe-oaths and proceedings, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly declaiming againſt them, as the direct road to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, and the very Devills preſcript to tumble men head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into hell, as <hi>Slades Caſe,</hi> 4. <hi>Report fol.</hi> 95.</p>
            <p>Now in direct oppoſition to all the ſore-cited Lawes, Statutes, Antiquities, Authorities, &amp;c. and contrary to the courſe of all other Courts of Juſtice (even of the Starre-Chamber while it continued) the Houſe of Lords did with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Summons, or other Proceſſe for appearance, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attach, apprehend, and impriſon your Petitioners husband, violently (by their Officers) breaking open, ſearching and ranſacking his houſe, felloniouſly taking away his goods, not ſaving to him his contenniment or livelihood, but alſo, before any Indictment, Preſentment, or other due Proceſſe of Law preceding, ſend forth their Officers againe to enter, ſearch, ranſack and rifle your Petitioners houſe, her trunks, cheſts, &amp;c. to rob, ſteal, plunder, and beare away her goods, which were her then preſent livelihood for her impriſoned husband, her ſelfe, and three ſmall children, her brother and ſiſter; and to bring your Petitioner, with <hi>Thomas Overton</hi> her husbands brother, unto their Prerogative-Barre, which was accordingly done. And by reaſon your Petitioner
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114071:4"/>
would not be ſubject to the arbitrarie and diabolicall accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomarie proceedings of that Houſe, to anſwer to Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, or to make oath againſt her husband or her ſelfe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his or her life, liberty, or goods, was, together with her ſaid Brother-in-Law, (himſelfe alſo refuſing ſubjection to the ſaid illegall proceedings) committed to the New Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in Maiden Lane, where he ſtill moſt unjuſtly remaineth, and is illegally detained: and from thence, under colour of another Arbitrary Order from the Houſe of Lords, your Petitioner, with her tender Infant in her armes of halfe a yeares age, was moſt inhumanely and barbarouſly dragged headlong upon the ſtones through all the dirt and the mire in the ſtreets, and by the way was moſt unjuſtly reproached and vilified by their Officers, with the ſcandalous, infamous names of wicked Whore, Strumpet, &amp;c. and in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, barbarous manner was caſt into the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull Goale of Bridewell, that common center of Whores, Strumpets, &amp;c. where from the 8. of January 1646. to this preſent, ſhe remaineth in cruell reſtraint, being moſt unnaturally and tyrannically divided and divorced by a forced ſeparation, from the comfort and ſociety of her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band in this her afflicted condition; her husband, her ſelfe, and her brother being impriſoned, and her three helpleſſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren expoſed to the mercy of the wide world; an act ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred of God, of Nature, of Nations, yea of the moſt wild and barbarous Heathens, of Turks, Infidels, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans. Which proceedings of theſe mercileſſe cruell Lords exceed all temporall exorbitant Vſurpers before them, in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, injuſtice, cruelty, and oppreſſion, being parallel'd by none but by the Spaniſh or Romiſh Inquiſitors: a tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call grievance and exorbitancie ſo exceſſive and intolerable, ſo contrary to all Law, equity and juſtice, that the Parliament 7. <hi>Iacobi</hi> in their Petition of Grievances exhibited to King <hi>Iames,</hi> and by ſundry Parliaments ſince, and by this preſent Parliament in their Remonſtrance of the 15. of December 1642. is complained againſt as an inſufferable Outrage, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glarie and oppreſſion, deſiring a ſpeedy reformation; upon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114071:5"/>
which they and you received royal promiſes, that thoſe exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitances ſhould be redreſſed: yet notwithſtanding this kind of inſufferable tyrannie, injuſtice, violence, inforced ſlaverie and oppreſſion of the Lords, through your neglect of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint and moderation, is now become more frequent and common then in any former ages, ſubjecting us under worſe ſlaverie, and greater and more exorbitant unlimited arbitrary power and uſurpation, then formerly we were by the Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, Star-Chamber and High-Commiſſion: yet when we have appealed to this Houſe both for judgement and redreſſe, all approaches to juſtice have beene interrupted and hitherto delayed, our Petitions and Complaints ſleightly rejected or diſregarded, our friends wearied, vexed and moleſted with long &amp; fruitles attendance, while we, our husbands, brethren, friends and ſervants, contrary to all Law (ſeverally, and in a forced and unjuſt ſeparation from our husbands) are kept and mewed up in your ſeverall ſtarving, ſtinking, murthering priſon-houſes, and if at any time we get acceſſe, or a Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on read, which is ſeldome obtained, we are referred over to one Committee or other, who never will bring their reports unto the Houſe, to the obſtructing and perverting the whole courſe of juſtice. Whereas the grand Traitors, the rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lords, who have been in armes againſt you, and other the profeſſed and known enemies of the Kingdome, yea ſome of the Rebells exempted from pardon in the Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſent to the King, can have liberty upon their paroll, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy their eſtates, obtaine favour and free acceſſe unto you, ready acceptance and hearing of their Petitions, quick diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patches of their buſineſſe: And notwithſtanding the great and urgent Affaires of the Kingdome (that common pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for the obſtruction and ſuſpenſe of the juſt and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary redreſſe of your beſt friends, and faithfull lovers of their countrey) you can finde leiſure, and take time weekly and daily to paſſe Ordinances for compoſitions and pardons for Delinquents, declared Traitors, ſomtimes twenty, ſomtimes more upon one day; to heare the Petitions of ſuch as are malevolently affected, not onely againſt your beſt, moſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114071:5"/>
faithfull untainted friends, aſſiſtants and adherents, but even againſt the ſinewes of yours and the Kingdomes defenſive might, the Army, endeavouring and ſupplicating their ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy diſſolution, and the removall of all the beſt affected, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven while there was a threatning, puiſſant Army of another Nation within the bowells of the Land, to paſſe Votes, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, Declarations, &amp;c. againſt preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, juſt as if you were running a tilt againſt Chriſt, to deſtroy, root out, and confound all ſuch as are religiouſly affected, and have been (under God) the very props and pillars of your houſe, the ſubduers and conquerers of yours and the Kingdomes enemies, and all under the ſacred pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of ſuppreſſion of Heretickes, Schiſmaticks, &amp;c. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of Hereſies, Schiſmes, Blaſphemies, &amp;c. and under that religious guiſe ſtab your friends to the heart; and when ſuch your faithfull oppreſſed Aſſiſtants come with their Petitions for redreſſe and caſe of their grievances, they are ordinarily ſleighted, ſcoffed and derided, even by the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of your Houſe: a moſt abhorred impiety, moſt bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous ingratitude! for theſe and ſuch like enormities and abuſes of the people, you can finde leiſure and opportunity enough, but you are ſo buſied with the great affaires of the Kingdome (as you call it) that you can find no time theſe ſixe years to proclaime liberty to the captive, freedome to the oppreſſed, to right the cauſe of the poore, to heare the cry of the fatherleſſe and widdow, to reforme the cruelties and extortions of Goalers, which like ſo many vulters upon a dead karkaſe, eat the fleſh, and pick the bones of thoſe poor miſerable ſoules that are caſt into their cuſtody; to protect or countenance the Commoners againſt the Prerogative u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpers and invaders of the great Charter of their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or to reſtraine or curb their inſolent aſpiring domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; to reſtore the Citie of London and other Cities, Towers and Burroughs to their antient Liberties and Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes; to diſrobe the London Gown-men of their Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive uſurpation of the freemens Property in the election of their publike Officers: to bring Delinquents amongſt you to triall,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114071:6"/>
to give encouragement to the people to bring in their juſt charge againſt any amongſt you, which ſhall betray their truſt, or deale treacherouſly with the people, Lawes, Free-Cuſtomes, or Liberties; to reforme the abuſes of the Law through all the Courts in the Kingdome, to cauſe the Lawes of the Land to be tranſlated out of Pedlars French and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, into the Engliſh Tongue, &amp;c. So that many begin to feare by theſe your delayes of juſtice, by your connivance at the Lords encreaſing uſurpations, and attonement with and pardons of the Kingdomes Enemies, by your diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements and ſleightings of your friends, you give way to the Lords to carrie on a deſigne to alter the whole frame of the Legall Government of the Land, and of ſubjection of us to a tyrannous, lawleſſe orbitrary Power, and vaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, to the totall overthrow and irrecoverable loſſe and ruine of all our juſt Rights, and native Liberties; for what is tyranny, but to admit no Rule of Government, but their wills, as with them by your permiſſion is familiar and frequent: and we know (as ſometimes the King hath told you) the miſery of Athens was at the higheſt, when it ſuffered under thirty Tyrants; and if inſtead of one Tyrant we have got three or foure hundred, we cannot be far from the height of ours.</p>
            <p>Now for as much as by the Lawes and Statutes of this Kingdome, no Juſtices or other Judges of the Realme can make a Warrant upon bare ſurmiſe to breake any mans houſe for a fellon, or for ſtollen goods (much leſſe for a free-mans owne) the ſame being againſt <hi>Mag. Charta cap.</hi> 29. and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Statute of 42. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3. &amp;c. and in this caſe before Indictment, neither the Conſtable nor any other man can breake open any mans houſe for the apprehenſion of the partie ſuſpected, or charged with Fellony, for it is in Law, the arreſt of the partie that hath the knowledge or ſuſpition, who cannot breake any houſe, 2. <hi>H.</hi> 7. 3. and 15. 4. <hi>H.</hi> 7 2 3. 5. <hi>H.</hi> 7. 4. 10. <hi>H.</hi> 7. 17. 20. <hi>H.</hi> 7. 12. 7. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4 20. 8. <hi>E.</hi> 4 3. 10. <hi>E.</hi> 4. 17. 9. <hi>E.</hi> 4 26. 11. <hi>E.</hi> 4. 4. 13. <hi>E.</hi> 4. 9. 7. <hi>H.</hi> 4. 35. 17. <hi>E.</hi> 4. 5. 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 23.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114071:6"/>
               <hi>Dier.</hi> 7. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 23. 6. <hi>Cooks Reports</hi> 1. 5. <hi>Fol.</hi> 9. 92. <hi>Semanies caſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as impriſonment by the Lords is inflicted by their cenſures as a puniſhment, and ſo their firſt impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before other Summons being no other then to begin exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution before hearing, which is contrary to all Law and Reaſon: And foraſmuch as juſtice and right is to bee done freely without faile, fully without deniall, and ſpeedily without delay, <hi>Quia dilatio eſt quaedam negatio;</hi> for ſo bee the words of the great Charter, <hi>We will deferre juſtice to no man, cap.</hi> 29. confirmed by the Statutes, 2. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 8. 14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 14. 20. <hi>E.</hi> 3, <hi>c.</hi> 1, 2. 11. <hi>Ric.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 11. And laſtly, for that no Act, Order, or Ordinance of the Lords binds the Subject without concurrence of this Honourable Houſe, as notably appeareth by ſeverall Records, <hi>An.</hi> 6. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 6. <hi>Rot. Clauſ. An.</hi> 44. <hi>E.</hi> 3. And the Lords plead a joynt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence for nullity of the proceedings and Compoſitions of Goldſmiths Hall.</p>
            <p>Your Petitioner therefore doth make her humble Appeale from the Juriſdiction of the Houſe of Lords, to the legall triall, judgement and determination of this Houſe, either for juſtification or condemnation, as by your Honours it ſhall be legally found.</p>
            <p>And ſhee humbly prayeth this honourable Houſe to take into your due and ſpeedy conſideration the miſerable diſtreſſe and deplorable condition of your Petitioner, her husband, and brother, long groaning under the oppreſſion and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the arbitrary and tyrannicall power of the Lords, who without fault or Law have caſt them into three ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall chargeable Goales, and ſomtimes have kept your Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners husband in double irons.</p>
            <p>And in regard the Committee for conſideration of the Commoners Liberties having taken your Petitioners huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands cauſe into their triall and judgement, and have for theſe three moneths deferred the report thereof unto this Houſe, concluded by the ſaid Committee, to the great miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and dammage of your Petitioner, her husband and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114071:7"/>
by reaſon of his long and tedious impriſonment (in expectation of the legall determination of this Houſe) to the great wrong and prejudice of the Peoples Liberties in the generall.</p>
            <p>It is therefore further the humble deſire of your Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that her husband, her ſelfe, and her brother, without further procraſtination and delay, may receive the juſt and ſpeedy ſentence of this Houſe accordingly as it ſhall bee le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally found and determined by the Vote of this Houſe; that in caſe by Law it ſhall be found that your Petitioners huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, her ſelfe and her brother have done ought worthy of death, or other exemplary puniſhment, that they may forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with receive their juſt execution accordingly. But and if your Petitioner, her husband and her brother bee legally found not guilty of any tranſgreſſion of the knowne Lawes of the Land, that then by an Order from this Houſe they may forthwith be diſcharged from under the vaſſallage and bondage of thoſe inſulting tyrannizing Lords; and that for the future you would be pleaſed to protect them and the reſt of their Nationall Brethren the free Commoners of England from the like Prerogative-inſolencies, cruelties and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: and that in caſe this Houſe by the Law of the Land ſhall finde your Petitioners husband, her ſelfe and her bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wronged and abuſed, that you would according to juſtice give them ful and ample reparations for their long and unjuſt impriſonment, like as you have done of late to ſundry of your owne Members your Petitioners Fellow Commoners; that you will not any longer deny them the benefit of the Law, which is their birthright and inheritance, and let them not be deprived of that which every monethly Seſſions you do allow to theeves and murtherers, to have a free and ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy triall: and as you can and doe without interruption of your other affaires, free and diſcharge your owne Servants and Attendants out of priſon the ſame or the next day after their commitments; ſo now at length, after ſo long atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, and ſo many moneths cruell and harſh impriſonment, let us receive the like impartiall ſpeedy juſtice.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:114071:7"/>And by reaſon your Petitioners husband, your Petitioner and her brother have choſen bonds and affliction under theſe Norman Prerogative-Task-maſters the Houſe of Lords, rather then they will for their parts yeeld up the birth-right and inheritance of the Commoners unto their Lordſhips Prerogative-juriſdiction. Let not therefore your Petitioners husband, her ſelfe and her brother be more unjuſtly and ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally dealt with then traitors, theeves and murtherers, but let them with ſuch have an equall benefit of the Law, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for ſpeedy penalty or preſent releaſe; which requeſt is ſo legall and reaſonable; that if it be by you denied, it will be a certaine evidence of your diſaffection to the Commonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of England, and of your evill intentions to their Lawes, Rights and Freedomes. And if for your Petitioners plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with you, and juſt deſires for redreſſe of her moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable grievances, you ſhall be provoked to exerciſe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cruelty and affliction either upon her ſelfe or her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, it will be a certain confirmation to all that ſhall heare of it (which ſhall be the whole Kingdome, if your Petitioners husband miſſe not of his aime) that you are abſolutely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, if poſſibly you can, to inſlave the Commons of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land to a Lordly arbitrary vaſſallage and bondage, to conquer and deſtroy their Lawes, Rights, Liberties and Freedomes, and to turn co-Vſurpers and joynt-Tyrants with that Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man brood of inſolent domineering Tyrants and Vſurpers, the Houſe of Lords.</p>
            <p>Doe therefore juſtice, and diſcharge your truſt unto the People, and do no leſſe unto us who have ingaged our ſelves, our lives and all for their Rights and Freedomes to well as for our owne, then you would be eſteemed to do unto all and every Commoner of England, but remove this grievous Norman Prerogative yoke of bondage from off our necks, and from the necks of all the free Commoners of England; then which nothing will more manifeſt your reall and cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all care and affection to the publike liberty and ſafety of the People, which is the Soveraigne Law, and for which all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114071:8"/>
Lawes are and ought to be made, and for no other end. And thus you ſhall in a high manner diſcharge your truſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the People, conciliate and beget their affections, their hearts, hands, &amp;c. and become the praiſe amongſt the people above all other Parliaments before you; and give juſt cauſe to your Petitioner, her husband, &amp;c. to bleſſe God for you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>And your Petitioner (as in duty bound) ſhall ever pray, &amp;c.</hi>
Per me <hi>Mary Overton.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:114071:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
